<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The city alarum, or The weeke of our miscarriages, which have hitherto obstructed our proceedings, and will now retard them, if not speedily removed. Whereunto is annexed a treatise of the excize.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 75 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79815</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4346</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E292_12</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200147</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860952</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860952</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113079</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79815)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113079)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 48:E292[12])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The city alarum, or The weeke of our miscarriages, which have hitherto obstructed our proceedings, and will now retard them, if not speedily removed. Whereunto is annexed a treatise of the excize.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Ioshua Kirton in Forster-Lane next Gold-Smiths Hall.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 7th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Excise tax --  Netherlands --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Taxes, Farming of --  Netherlands --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113079:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CITY ALARVM, OR The Weeke of our miſcarriages, Which have hitherto obſtructed our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, and will now retard them, if not ſpeedily removed. Whereunto is annexed a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of the EXCIZE.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Luke <hi>14.28.29.30.</hi> verſes.</bibl>
               <p>For which of you intending to build a Tower, ſitteth not downe firſt, and counteth the coſt whether he have ſufficient to finiſh it?</p>
               <p>Leſt haply after he hath laid the foundation, and is not able to finiſh it, all that behold it, begin to mocke him,</p>
               <p>Saying This man began to build, and was not able to finiſh.</p>
            </q>
            <q>Chi dinanzi non mira, di dietro poi ſospira.</q>
            <p>London Printed for <hi>Ioſhua Kirton</hi> in <hi>Forſter-Lane</hi> next Gold-Smiths Hall. 1645.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:113079:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113079:2"/>
            <head>The City Alarum.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S in naturall ſo in Politicke Bodies, the ready way to perfection is a frequent and impartiall view of their own abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and defects, &amp; looke how much theſe are uſually Supernumerary, ſo much the more aſſiduity is required in their ſearch: conſervation, which is groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon a right underſtanding of our wants, in the very categorie of nature preceds acquiſition, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of imminent danger, the improveme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of advantages.</p>
            <p>Therefore flatterers are worthily exploded, as the moths of vertue and underminers of merit, who by giving men falſe intelligence of themſelves, and correſponding with our hereditary enemy, ſelf love, hinder us from perſuing the moſt glorious of all Victories, that of our owne imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. I mean not Princes earewigs, the ſceane is now al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd, court and court pariſites vaniſhed together: there is a negative as well as affirmative flattery, by ſilencing our failings as well as over extolling our merits. Is't not ſtrange that among us who fight for truth it ſhould be malignancy to ſpeake it? We are contented to ly complaining in the mire, rather then ſtrive to riſe, every child whiſpers, no man ſpeaks out our miſcarriages, and how thinke we to be cured if we conceale our wounds, the maine part of the cure conſiſting in the tenting? Ther's no good fencing without knowledge of the feeble of your Sword, and in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification we eſteeme that engineer a traytour, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceales
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113079:3"/>or leſſens a places weaknes, firſt repaire breaches, then make a ſally.</p>
            <p>Not many weeks are paſt ſince I exchanged forraigne aire for Engliſh. I have heard of a miſterious way of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating intelligence between perſons far diſtant, by vertue of the Load-ſtone, ſure I am, the ſame <hi>Load-ſtone,</hi> which toucht you at home, affected me abroad, and I might well make excurſions with my thoughts, but their continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all revolution was about your affaires, ſo that in what Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat ſoever I was, I felt the aire of our Engliſh newes very catching, more eſpecially it grieved me exceedingly to heare of our home bred jarres, animoſity and partiality whereby we curtail'd our ſtrength more ſhamefully then <hi>Hanun</hi> did <hi>Davids</hi> Meſſengers, expoſing our nakedneſſe to the view of all the world, an object of pitty to our friends, of ſcorne and deriſion to our enemies.</p>
            <p>The Parliaments friends abroad have hitherto looked upon their party, as upon a goodly well built body, ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly limb'd, and fairly proportioned only hindred in its growth and thriving, by ſome ſleeping ill humor whereby it waſted and pined a way no man knew how, ſo that they commiſerated and prayed for us, but thought us irrecovera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by any other Phyſitian, then God and Time.</p>
            <p>Now that by Gods mercifull providence this occult evill humour is broken out into botches and boyles all over our body, (one great impoſtume already broken, others rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to breake, if ſeaſonably cruſhed,) inſtead of rejoycing at ſignes of health, we bemoane our loſſe of beauty, looking backe (whiles we ſhould march forward) to our faire armies in the old Modell, between whoſe ceremonious proceedings, and thoſe of the new, there is as great difference, as between the Law and the Goſpell. And if not the vaſteſt but moſt ſpirited body, be the uſefulleſt, I know no reaſon why we ſhould not make more account of this little army, although
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113079:3"/>but like <hi>Naam ans</hi> fleſh recovered of his leaproſy, comming againe as a childs, then of all our former brawny armies, Men are to be weighed, not numbred, and to be weighed by their uſefullneſſe, a little treaſure expended doing more good then a great deale hoarded up.</p>
            <p>But what advantageth it us to have begun well, if we ſtop in the middle of the race? Or to have projected a good Plan, if we neglect the ſuperſtructure, perchance we thinke the name of a new Moddell a ſufficient ſpell, without any further proviſion, or hath not indeed ſelf intereſt bribed ſome mens paſſions to rebell againſt their reaſons, who not able to hinder the make of this engine, now ſtrive to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pede its motion, ſome of theſe having moſt unworthily tranſported what they could out of the ſhip of the ſtate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their owne cockboats, now thinke to ſet up ſayle in a miſt undeſcried, like ſilly birds who thruſting their heads into a buſh thinke no body ſees them, but however they turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way their eyes from their own unworthineſſe yet others ſee it, and God will puniſh it.</p>
            <p>In the meane time it concernes all men of integrity to rub their eyes, and inquire out the reaſons of our reſtive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which hath brought us upon precipices before we were aware, and which will infallibly ruine us, (I ſpeak in a rationall ſence) if not ſpeedily remedied.</p>
            <p>I am not ſo childiſh as to imagine my eye ſight ſharper then other mens, yet a boy upon a Theater may ſee more then a man in a crowd, and a ſtander by ſometimes you know, ſees more then a Gameſter. I eaſily believe, moſt men apprehend the danger we are in, but either willfully ſhun the thoughts of it, as contagious; or amazed with the horror therof, ſtand gazing with croſſed armes, as if they were metamorphoz'd into Marble, while the weaker ſort of people, like the Sea when mov'd with a tempeſt, roare and beat themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the rocks, which they ſhould rather ſtrive with uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113079:4"/>force to eſchew, by ſtrugling againſt the waves, which have caſt us upon them. All in generall make difficulties, which ſhould be wherſtones to their courage, graveſtones to their reſolutions, wherefore that I may not be guilty of the ſame ſin of omiſſion I condemne in others, I will endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour a diſcovery of the chiefe Remoras, which I conceave to flick in our wheeles, with a rude draught of their removall, which wiſer men may perfect.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Spaniards</hi> reward thoſe Meſſengers beſt, who bring worſe tydings, whereby their loſſes being timely redreſſed, ſeeme rather ſlips then falls, and they are no ſooner downe then up againe. I expect no ſuch welcome of my unſavory intelligence, as meer duty raviſhed it from my breaſt, ſo the diſcharge thereof, is all my pretended recompence. Yet I confeſſe my ſatisfaction would be doubled, if by ringing this Alarum, I could awake all thoſe in this City, whom it concernes, to ſhake off that frozen timidity, which a little winter of adverſity, hath cauſed in them, and reveſt their wonted courage, which now ſeems to lie bedrid.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Now to our Scrutiny.</head>
               <p>ALL affaires move upon the two hindges of counſell and action, deliberation and execution, whereof that ſeems to be as the head, this as the feet of every great enterprize, or if you will, the braine conceives, and the hand is the braines midwife. When either of theſe is out of tune, the conſort is ſpoyled, both pilot and mariners muſt concur to guide the Veſſell. No wonder if our feet ſayled us in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and that our numerous Armies did ſo little, their joynts were goury. The Commander ſteered by a meere defenſive principle, went a way to plaiſter, not cure our wound, and the common Souldier ſoone caught with the bird-lime of profit, was eaſily perſwaded to keep out of gunſhot, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenting themſelves to give us once in a yeare a bit of action
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113079:4"/>to ſtay our ſtomacks: whereas in our caſe not ſpeedily to conquer, was to be conquered; for ſeeing our ſtrength was then in its flower, the Kings only growing, to expect, was but to give his Forces time to accompliſh their growth, and draw a decrepitneſſe upon our owne. It's eaſie traverſing the head of a Spring, but now that we have travelled along the bank-ſide, till this Spring is ſwollen into a mighty River, we find it impaſſable.</p>
               <p n="1">1. I would not have looked ſo far back, having ſo much mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter before me, were not the ſame gouty humour, of late eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, crept into the upper Region of our body. Have we not ſome envious ſpirits (an infallible indice of ſelf-empti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of worth) who ſit in the manger, neither doing nor ſuffering others to doe any thing? <hi>qui jettent la pierre &amp; cachent le bras.</hi> Theſe State juglers, are the States greateſt enemies, who by underboord working conjure up ſuch fog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy fumes into our head, that our eyes dazzle: our Counſels rurne round, and ſuch a thick miſt hath benighted our underſtandings, that few ſee upon what ground we ſtand. But wherefore all this intricacy? I anſwer, ſome gouty old Members now out of joynt, ſtrive to ſlip in againe in the dark, which to effect, they have attempted to put the whole body out of frame, wherein they were not a little incoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, conſidering there are as many Drones as Bees in the hive, and the Bees more laden with wax then honey, their wiſdome miſcarrying through abundance of facility.</p>
               <p>Thus our ague is turn'd into a Feaver, the diſtemper of our feet, into a diſtemper of the braine, to teach us that the chaine of humane affaires is never compleat, either the linke of will, or linke of power is wanting: for now that we have a gallant and faithfull Army, deſirous to improve advantages, their wings muſt be pinion'd with expectation of Orders, whiles in the mean time opportunity ſteals out of ſight, which can only be hunted at view, not by ſcent. Moſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113079:5"/>buſineſſes ſuffer ſhipwrack, becauſe occaſions are haſty, and men ſlow, eſpecially in war, occaſions once loſt are irreco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verable. Haſt is the beſt friend, when time is the greateſt enemy, as it needs muſt now be ours, when as our ſtrength is in its virility and age of conſiſtency, and cannot but in reaſon expect its decaying age to enſue; wherefore before arrant imbecility ſeize us, we ſhould do well with all intentneſs to put out our ſtrength to the uttermoſt. To which end no meanes would be more effectuall then a ſtanding Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee in our Army, of ſuch as are well affected to our new Modell, who as freſh ſpirits to the body, may adde life and motion thereunto: All advantage in war conſiſting in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain emergencies, which are ſwift in their paſſage, admit of no delay, but muſt be apprehended on the place: and howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver this hint may ſeem poſthumous, the thing being already done (thankes to the City Petition;) yet I leave to wiſer conſideration, whether we may not juſtly feare new rubs and ſtops in the proſecution of this miraculous ſucceſſe, wherewith God hath bleſſed us, as long as thoſe who have proclaim'd their diſaffection by the opprobrious terme of <hi>new noddell,</hi> have any ſhare in its diſpoſall.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Some are the backwarder in proviſion for this Army, becauſe they feare the advantage thereof will rebound upon the Independents, and the heat given thereunto, hatch more of that faction; as if we were ſtill in a condition, to pick and chooſe. Is not the City exhauſted, the Country in moſt places waſted, every where diſcontented, our Coffers emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied, our ſpirits halfe ſpent, and all ſtrugling for life, and yet we muſt cut off the only ſound limbe we have left, becauſe, forſooth, it goes not ſo regularly as we could wiſh. Cannot lines meet all in one point; though they goe not all the ſame way? they may often meet, yet differ. Though ſpeech is neceſſary for all men, yet not this or that language, ſo diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline Eccleſiaſticall is generally requiſite, but not materiall
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113079:5"/>whether the way be left greene or paved. It were to be wiſhed Chriſtian charity and diſcretion had both, had more ſway among us, as well Presbyterians as Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants, whoſe imbittered zeale one againſt the other hath been ſo heady and prepoſterous, as if men thought the only way to be ripe in faith, were to be raw in wit; whereas the only way not to be inveagled by the guilefull through skill, is to be skilfull againſt guile. Truth hath no ſuch enemy as likelihood, Satan is never ſo terrible, as when hee appeares like an Angell of light, preſenting ſpecious, but falſe appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, to animate us one againſt another, and cut aſunder all ligaments and ſinewes of unity, well knowing that the ſtrength of the fagot conſiſts in the bond. Weighty is defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by <hi>Plato,</hi> that which is made up of moſt parts of the ſame nature, light, that which hath feweſt; therefore ſtones ſinke, when great beams ſwim. If we deſire a true eſtimate of our ſtrength, we muſt meaſure it by our unity. What a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailes it to overcome others, whiles our diſſentions conquer us? Diſſention makes us float in uncertainty, Unity only is able to bring us to the ground. I hate irrationability in whom ſoever I find it, and can wiſh thoſe <hi>Nadabs</hi> and <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hues,</hi> who have offered up new and ſtrange fires, no worſe puniſhment then to be ſtill guided by their <hi>ignes fatui.</hi> But the paſſion of ſome, ſhould not make us paſſionate againſt all: if we lay aſide prejudicacie, and examine the unſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reaſons, ſome out of animoſity alledge againſt employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing active Independents at this time, we ſhall find them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble the colours of the rainbow, which are but ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary, and vaniſh for want of ſubſiſtance in a ſolid body. And whatever ſome men conceive of their opinions in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the State, were it not madneſs for feare of a future miſchief to make it preſent? as if for feare of dying ſo many years hence, a man ſhould preſently become his proper exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioner: of two evils being not both avoydable, the choyce
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113079:6"/>of the leſſe is not evill. Were it not folly in a ſtorme to refuſe the ayde of ſome, becauſe their clothes and ours were of a different faſhion? thoughts and opinions are the appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell of the mind; and if the greatneſs of our miſery had not depriv'd us of the ſenſe thereof, we ſhould eſteeme thoſe our beſt friends, who firſt bring us aſhore, and employ the forwardeſt men with what opinion ſoever clad, as the fitteſt means to make an end of the worke, which elſe will ſoon make an end of us.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Next to our diſtractions, nothing hath ſo much dampt the vigour of our proceedings, as our antidated and abbor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive hopes of finall ſucceſſe, grounded upon preſumptuous thoughts of our owne ſtrength, and our enemies weakneſs; whereby it hath many times come to paſſe, that meaſuring our enemies rather then our ſelves, and that by the diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive glaſſe of our ſimpring intelligence, we have made our Armies, as ſome bad Taylors do childrens clothes, too juſt to the body of our enterprize; not conſidering the infinite conſequence of a loſt battell, whereto we expoſe our ſelves, at leaſt if we win: having not men enough preſently to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue a Victory, a valiant enemy ſelling it, perhaps, ſo deare, that our Army is compelled to loſe the fruits thereof, we are forced to prolong the war, exhauſting men and treaſure, till the proceſſe, though won, coſts more then the thing is worth. The calling back part of our Forces before the work was wholly finiſhed, hath likewiſe coſt us deare, witneſſe the late buſineſſe of <hi>Taunton.</hi> He that deſpiſes his enemy, puts not out halfe his force, and that with little intentneſs, wheras a little well-knit man, by wary husbanding his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, often caſts a mightier, blinded with this paſſion.</p>
               <p>The diſeaſe is growne epidemicall, our eares are ſo deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, they are galled with the rehearſall of truth, its a meat of too hard digeſtion for our tender ſtomacks, as if it were not ſafer to give two falſe alarums, then neglect one true,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113079:6"/>petty dangers may ſometimes be wiſely concealed for ſeat of uproars, but apparent perills ought to be expounded to the people, leaſt whereas they are great, they be thought deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate. How can we make an even encounter, when we are ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of the length of our adverſaries weapon? Yet now a dayes its malignancy to diſcover it: who ever makes a true map of the Kings ſtrength is reckoned among the Iſraelitical meſſengers, who brought up an evill report of the land of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> a diſheartner of Gods people; Sure they have but <hi>Pigmy</hi> ſpirits who dare not ſtand a relation of the Royall <hi>Anakims.</hi> But this uneveneſſe of ſpirit, is ſelf conceits conſtant hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid, the fall is uſuall from the pinacle of preſumprion to the dungeon of deſpaire. Its obſervable, how we have alwaies hood winkt our ſelves with conceits of the kings impuiſſance till it came to tryall, and then finding him ſtronger then we ſuſpected, we ſuſpect him ſtronger then indeed he is, it being naturall for one contrary to beget another.</p>
               <p>Hope is the fawning traytor of the mind, whiles under colour of freindſhip it robs it of its cheifeſt ſtrength, reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution. This over early expectance of an end of our trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, diſinables us in the means, and is as much before time, as our dilatory proceedings are out of time.</p>
               <p>Hence flow preſent and tumultuary counſels, without any proviſion for the future, circumferentiall deliberations without any fixed center. No wonder then if every unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected accident, whereof War is full, ſets the Sun-diall of our counſells ten degrees backward, ſince tis the nature of ſudden and unlookt for danger, to ſurpriſe and ſuſpend the uſe of reaſon. Experience is the miſtreſſe of fooles, but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt the mother of wiſdome, becauſe doubting the worſt, it repreſents future miſcheif as preſent, and provides a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, if we had begun with doubts, we had ended long agoe in certainties, but becauſe we began with certainties, therefore we remain in doubts. There is no prudence with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an eye in the forehead, or policy without foreſight,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113079:7"/>neither is foreſight availeable without application of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventive phyſick. At the firſt we had undoubtedly a foregame, of late we have been forced to alter our ward, and play an aftergame, which our gamſters have ſo well managed, that we begin to ſet up all our ſayles again. People naturally flow in confidence, ebbe in deſpaire, And from the colliſion of theſe two waves, ariſes the foame of impatience: checke me this peccant humour and provide for the War, as if it were to continue a hundred years, then with Gods bleſſing, it may end in one: we muſt worke out our ſalvation here, as well as hereafter, with feare and trembling.</p>
               <p n="4">4. A concomitant hereof is our greedy graſping of more buſineſſe then we are able to wield, this vice hath been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominate both in our Counſels and actions: Our ſtriving to reforme all at once hath made us reforme nothing, for as it is not good to paſſe by the leaſt errour in an intire Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, ſo in a corrupt one to appear too much a good Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealths man, is the next way to ruine it; the ſame weight which preſervs in ſafety an upright pillar, cauſeth it to fall, if the pillar leane. State alterations are beſt graduall. Our paſſionate deſire of an end, recoyles us from the end, whileſt we embrace the moſt ſpecious not the moſt feaſable deſignes,<note place="margin">Oxfords <hi>ſeidge and</hi> Liceſters <hi>loſſe.</hi>
                  </note> looking more at what ſhould be done, then at what can be done, and weighing only the conveniences of a deſigne ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, but forgetting to put into the ballance, the difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the effecting, the inconveniences other parts ſuffer in the Interim, the gaine of the enemy, who like a river over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing its banks carries all before him, for want of our timely oppoſing a Digue to ſtop the torrent. Whereto have ſo many blockings, ſerv'd but for ſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bling blocks to our friends, bridges to our enemies; who have oftentimes eat the meat, whiles we were knawing the bones. Have we not loſt whole countreys while like flies, we were buzzing about ſome glim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mering enterpriſe, where many times we burnt our wings
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113079:7"/>into the bargaine? <hi>Chi troppo abbraccia nulla ſtrigne,</hi> he that will do all, ſhall do nothing, nay worſe then nothing. War is too ſlippery a way to ſtand at a ſtay in, we muſt either ſlide forward or backward; and if we ſtand ſtill, while the King goes forward, may we not properly be ſaid to looſe ground? We do worſe then ſtand ſtill, in doing things by halves. Its diſadvantagious to a private man to have too great an opinion of his merit preconceived, for Ideas are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies perfecter then Exiſtences, and men finding not what they expected, ſlight what they find: much more dangerous is it to States to occaſion a greater expectation in the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, then can be anſwer'd, and we occaſion it by the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplicity of our undertakings, which hath not only diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted our forces, exhauſted the well-affected (whoſe ſubven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as certaine, ſhould have been reſerved to a time of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant neceſſity,) and by both diſinabled us to any buſineſſe of importance, (for which we are alwaies forced to go a begging,) but it drawes an inevitable conſequence of lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving moſt things undone and doing all the reſt by halves.</p>
               <p>Its incredible how much this humour of not purſuing the point of our deſignes, hath diminiſhed our reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion abroad;<note place="margin">Picolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini.</note> 'Twas the cenſure of one of the greateſt ſouldiers this age hath produced, that the King and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were like two ill Gameſters at Cheſſe, who make many remooves to little purpoſe, neither of both skillfull enough to give checke mate: how it ſquares with the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all party, I know not, but feare he lighted too unhappily on us, we dance about the boord, run round like a horſe in a mill, and find our ſelves at the years end, where we were in the beginning: every man is ſenſible of this circular miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheif, but none mounts up to the cauſe, I will give you my thoughts thereon, only as they may relate to the future.</p>
               <p>Its a great ſecret in war, when there are many gaps to ſtop, to know, which it imports moſt to ſtop firſt. Herein
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113079:8"/>conſiſts the ſupreme degree of military prudence, and as it were the pretious Elixar, which we muſt ſeeke out to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happie this war, by labouring to diſcerne, which ought to be its principall ſeat, and to bend our powers thitherward, ready to change our conduct, as the war ſhall change its face. And becauſe this ſeems to be of no ſmall conſequence, give me leave to tell you the Spaniards proceeding herein, which is admirable and thrice worthy imitation.</p>
               <p>That which makes them poſſeſſe in perfection this ſecret, ſo that they are ſeldome cozened in the choice of what is moſt advantagious to their preſent affaires, is the Symme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie of their government, and ſubordination of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, which are divers, according to the ſeverall Territories of their domination, where their Armies are employed. For example.</p>
               <p>For the affaires of <hi>Italie,</hi> there is one Counſell eſtabliſh'd in <hi>Italie</hi> it ſelfe, which is formed by the correſpondence and relation, obſerved between their Miniſters there entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, eſpecially between the Governour of <hi>Milan,</hi> Viceroy of <hi>Naples,</hi> and two Embaſſadours of <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Venice.</hi> In oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currencies then which concern this Countrey, the firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberations are taken by theſe foure, who conſtitute as it were the firſt Tribunal, where the difficulties are agitated, and the reſolutions taken of what is moſt expedient to be done: the reſult of their adviſe, with a faithfull relation of the facts whereon it was formed, and reaſons whereon it was grounded, is ſent into <hi>Spaine</hi> to a ſecond Counſel, compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of perſons intelligent in Italian affaires, who by having paſſed through the greateſt employments of that Countrey, have great lights, and exact notions thereof; Here the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the firſt Counſel are put into the furnace again, and digeſted anew. And as in the Oeconomie of mans body, the ſpirits which are form'd in the liver, purifie themſelves in the heart, and diſcharge themſelves there, of what ever they have groſſe in them, before they come to the braine,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113079:8"/>where they receive the laſt degree of ſubtilitie and light, whereof they are capable, and obtaine a certaine vigorous quality, which renders them the moſt immediate organs of the bodies motion, and ſenſes operation: ſo the reſolutions of this ſecond Counſel, are carried to a third, which is the Princes Counſel of State, there to undergo a third Examen, and ſee if there be any room for them in the order of his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, and whether that, which relates to the good of <hi>Italy,</hi> (whereat only the two firſt Counſels aimed,) would not prejudice the generall good of their Monarchy. I have been the more punctuall in this deſcription, becauſe I judged it applicable to our preſent way of Eaſterne, Weſtern, Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne Committees, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> wherein were there a right ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination ſetled from thoſe in the Countrey to thoſe here, and from theſe to a third grand Committee, we ſhould not tread thoſe Mazes of fortune, wherein we have often wooded.</p>
               <p>We muſt reſolve to endure ſmall loſſes in one part, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine great ſucceſſe in another, for the branches will wither, when the trunck of the tree is rooted up, and when the vitals are wounded, the other parts die of themſelves.</p>
               <p>We unbend in good ſucceſſe, &amp; proſperitie ſeems to ſoften and melt our vigour; its too ſtrong a licour for our weak veſſels. We uſually <hi>crack</hi> till we <hi>break,</hi> we ſtop, as it were, to take breath, in the faireſt part of our way, and letting good fortune go before us, without having the courage to follow her, we looſe the ſight of her. Wheras we ſhould never repoſe leſſe then after ſucceſſe, nor ever be more deſirous to fight then after a battel, or to re-enter the carriere then after ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been crowned. What profits it us to have had ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the advantage in the race, while the King hath recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered it in the turne, and when we thought we had him in our armes, he hath ſlipt away between our legs.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Another main obſtruction in our Counſels hath been
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113079:9"/>want of ſecreſie, which is the life of conſultation, as expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition is of action, and here I muſt tell you plainly the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of ſtrangers, who thinke it impoſſible, the bell of our counſels ſhould ſound ſo loud, if ſome clappers did not ſpeake on both ſides, or that the King ſhould ſo eaſily un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold our riddles if he plowed not with ſome of our cattell. All is not gold that gliſters, and its feared if ſome great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended zealots both to Religion and Liberty were well rub'd they would prove but <hi>Alchimy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our greateſt enemies ſit at our tables, lie in our boſomes and as the heat which roſts the meat on the ſpit, is inviſible but by its effects; ſo we feele an unnaturall heat, gnaw and conſume our very entralls, but either cannot or will not yet diſcerne it. Sure <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Hall breeds ſpiders, although it breed no cobwebs; for the Royalliſts abroad could in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme me better of what paſt in Parliament, then the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Agents. Shal not this be ſearched out? Poore <hi>England,</hi> what! Diſperited ſo ſoone? <hi>London,</hi> what! ſo ſuddenly diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimated? you, whoſe dread hath been uppon forraign na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, what! ſuffer your ſelves now to be mated by a ſett or ſect of home bred <hi>Achitophells?</hi> ſhall wicked men dare to offend, and honeſt men not dare to puniſh? or will the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage perhaps not pay your paines? The routing of a trayterous crue may prove as advantagious, as the gaine of a battell, ſince by their treachery, we are liable to the loſſe of many battels.</p>
               <p>Beſides its more unſufferable to looſe by deceit then by force, becauſe cozenage is built by others craft upon the foundation of our inconſiderateneſſe. Neither let conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of former merit plead pardon for preſent miſdeeds but rather further puniſhment, as upon thoſe who having ſhown they knew how to do good, would againſt knowledge do evill. But pardon this tranſport which pure zeale to my Nation hath extorted from me, and jealouſy of its reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113079:9"/>on wherein I know how much we ſuffer in forraigne parts.</p>
               <p>When the <hi>Venetians</hi> ſuſpect any <hi>Patrician</hi> of correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence with a forraigne ſtate, they at the ſame time impriſon his perſon, &amp; ſearch his houſe. For State affaires, like mines, as ſoone as they take aire looſe their force, and evaporate into ſmoake. Therefore the Spaniards, who are their craftſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in the art of governing, are as diligent in concealing their deſignes, as if they wrought in ſome new found Peru; they ſeeme to repoſe and ſleep, when moſt buſy and broa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt awake: They are content to be accuſed of weakneſſe, and themſelves ſow abroad apparent reaſons, and furniſh ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious colours, to render this accuſation probable. By this means they lull a ſleep, and ſurprize, <hi>lightning</hi> upon their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies before they heare the <hi>thunder,</hi> and both hiſtory and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience teach us what incredible advantage they have ſometimes reaped hereby, and what prodigious blows they have given.</p>
               <p>Since we are ſo far in, it will not be amiſſe before we come out of this Spaniſh roade, to eye their dexterity in picking the lockes of other Princes cabinets, as well as dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble locking their owne: for ſince the knowledge of facts, and of the true eſtate of things is the baſe of ratiocination, and, if that be looſe this muſt needs be tottering; they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide two wayes againſt this inconvenience.</p>
               <p n="1">1. By giving power unlimited to their Agents, to ſpare no manner of coſt to be rightly informed of all paſſages, and to penetrate the deliberations and reſolutions of both friends and enemies, the expenſe is allowed them, without any examen or reſtriction, upon a bare note of their preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
               <p>And although this ſeeme to furniſh matter of cozenage and to open a field where covetouſneſſe may make an unjuſt harveſt, yet they chuſe rather to run this hazard, which is inconſiderable in reſpect of the great benefit they may
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113079:10"/>reap thereby, and they believe that any expenſe well made and one ſeaſonable advice, payes them with intereſt, for a hundred fruitleſſe disburſements, and improfitable adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſements.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Then, never were people in this world ſo induſtrious as they, to cheriſh their correſpondencies and thoſe in great number, they affect not only ſpecious ones, and with men of high birth and wiſedome; they entertaine who ever will be their Penſioners, having found by experience that a man of meane condition and parts, will ſometimes diſcloſe unto them an important truth which hath eſcaped the care and Sagacity of an illuſtrious perſonage. So that I have often been aſtoniſhed at the multitude of their Secretaries, and at the incredible number of letters which their Ambaſſadours diſpatch by all ſortes of Meſſengers.</p>
               <p>We need not goe to <hi>Madrit</hi> to exemplify this miſtery, we may ſee the conſequence thereof in the Kings procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, who hath done more by <hi>London</hi> Intelligence, then by <hi>Oxford</hi> force: although he payed dearly for his truſt to this Intelligence at <hi>Naſeby,</hi> where the inſtitution of our new Modell was ſealed from heaven with Gods approbation, and our diſpiſed army did that, may make envy it ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed. Wherefore the miraculous ſucceſſe, wherewith God hath crowned our cloſe uniting in the army, ſhould a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimate us to ſearch out the accurſed thing, which impea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches our union both in Parliament and City: the want whereof bars us of forraigne aide as well as good opinion, for when I have preſſed upon them in the low Countries, their intereſt involved in ours, many have expreſt great forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to aſſiſt us, if once they could, for their ſecurity ſee us unanimous, to aſſiſt our ſelves. And take this by the way, that thoſe people owe more for their liberty to their * firſt Generalls exact intelligence from <hi>Spaine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">W.P: <hi>of</hi> Orange.</note> then to all his and their armies: in ſence whereof they allow the Prince
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113079:10"/>of <hi>Orange</hi> every ſummer a tun or two of gold without exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, for Intelligence. If we weigh the premiſes, and how much we have ſuffer'd by our crazy Intelligence, we ſhall account it hereafter good husbandry to be prodigall in this particular; or if we will continue to be <hi>penny wiſe, and pound fooliſh,</hi> we muſt not wonder if our reſolutions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue likewiſe to be uncertaine, ſince built upon uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; for how can the building be firme, which is founded on quickſands?</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Dall'acque chete me ne guardi Iddio;</l>
                  <l>Che dalle correnti mene guardero Io.</l>
               </q>
               <p n="6">6. And now I have done with the cracks and flawes of the houſe, give me leave to hint at thoſe of the field, for all reflect upon the publike. I need not inſiſt on former abuſes, of hurrying the poor willing country people to &amp; fro, as if they had been ſo many puppetts for our Grandees to play withall Summoning them to appeare one moneth with Horſe, arms, and mony of their owne, and diſmiſſing them the next, tire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them out with continuall expectation of action, til they were unfit for action; as if their only deſigne had been by theſe mocke proceedings to render them either unable or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to help the State in time of reall neceſſity; to the infinite prejudice and diſhonour of the Parliament, who have by this meanes loſt many thouſand hands, if not hearts.</p>
               <p>But that which is <hi>inſtar omnium</hi> and the Serpentive a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe that hath devoured the memory of all other, is the <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence</hi> (for it exceeded the bounds of liberty) <hi>of free quarter,</hi> in Counties well affected. The rod of <hi>Moſes</hi> was turned into a ſerpent, and thoſe who were rayſed to defend us from oppreſſion moſt oppreſſed us. The inſolency of the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier baniſhed honeſt Gentlemen from their own houſes, and the Commonalty hereby left like a boat in a ſtorme a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon'd by its pilots, let themſelves drive, at the mercy of the wind and waves; ſo that few of note remaining among
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113079:11"/>them beſides Malignants, no wonder if the honeſt were ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, the wavering perverted, and the Malignant hardned in their obſtinacy, by our miſcariages. Whereto if we adde the inſupportable burdens layed on the ſhoulders of the well-minded party both in City and Countrey, with the little care taken for their future caſe, we need not go far to ſeeke the cauſe why ſo few, notwithſtanding our conqueſts, leave the Kings ſhadow to put themſelves under the Parliaments wings: for who will be his friend, that treats his friend worſe then his enemy? Muſt the free horſe alwayes be ſpur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galled, and the dull Aſſe favoured in his opiniatneſs? ſhall the moſt affectionate, be ſtill moſt ſqueezed? Patience abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, you know, turnes into fury. Popular inſurrections, like Mines, cannot be avoyded, but by foreſeeing them. Our cauſe ſtands upon two legs, Religion, and Liberty: if we rub too hard, we may perchance rub off many friends to the latter. Take heed how we irritate theſe; The taking away their livelihood is the only injury which admits of no obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vion, want being a continuall ſpur unto revenge. As the ſtomack, which is the ſeat of naturall heat, as long as it hath in it any nouriſhment, leaves the body in peace; but if al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together without, it then drawes nouriſhment from the head, and thereby often deſtroys the body: ſo as long as the people have ſome matter of ſubſiſtance left, they reſt ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, but when wholly deprived thereof, turne head upon their head, and often ruine the Common-wealth.</p>
               <p>People are eaſilier ruled with the <hi>ſnaffle</hi> of love, then with the <hi>bitt</hi> of feare: love is a ſilken thred, ſoon broken by harſh handling. We ride the people every journey, as if we ſhould never have occaſion more to come o'th' back of them: if we ride too hard, we may quickly run them out of breath, then ſtumble, and both finally fall together.</p>
               <p>I confeſſe, either my eyes faile me, or I cannot ſee how the Royalliſts themſelves could have chalked out a broader way
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113079:11"/>to our deſtruction, then that we have hitherto troden. For do but conſider ſeriouſly what a horrid gulfe of danger, we had throwne our ſelves into by theſe extemporary courſes, if the late inſulting enemy had prevailed, as what Patent had we to preſume of victory? Having diſ-inabled our truſtieſt friends, diſobliged others, and diſcontented all, whence could we in reaſon expect ſupply? you will ſay, from heaven. Sure, I know no promiſe, whereby God hath bound him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to incloſe thoſe, who breake downe their own hedges: Sure I am, the ſame God who <hi>commands</hi> innocency, <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends</hi> wiſdome as the others beſt guardian. I have obſerved ſome of opinion, that this worke will never be finiſhed with apparent means, becauſe they have remarked Gods arme higheſt lifted up againſt our enemies, in the loweſt ebb of our fortune. The root of this opinion is doubtleſs ſweet, <hi>viz.</hi> humility, but the fruit, I am ſure, is bitter: its like <hi>Ezekiels</hi> rowle, honey in the mouth, but gall and wormwood in the belly: whiles we feare to relye too much upon means, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God, we preſume too much upon God without means. Preſumption, is the fault of the men, not meanes; of the workmen, not inſtruments, which ought no more therefore to be caſhired, then the uſe of phyſicke, becauſe <hi>Aſa</hi> tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted to it more then God. To extrinſecate my ſelfe more plainely, this opinion is ſpawned by ignorance of our condition. For conſider firſt what a thred of time the German wars have ſpun out, beyond all expectation; we imagining long ſince, that <hi>every day</hi> would uſher in the <hi>evening</hi> of their troubles: The Proteſtant cauſe there, is as good as ours is here. 2. Conſider, what difficulty the Scots find, in ſweeping away a little rubbiſh in their Northerne quarters, with the force of their whole Kingdome. And tell me now, what cauſe of confidence we can pick out of our owne ſtrength, were it twice as big as now it is: ſince while we are Actors by winning, we loſe and ſuffer by working,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113079:12"/>waſting our force with uſing it, and like Bees, while we hurt others, loſe our ſting. The evill ſpirit of war is ſooner ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed then layed; like the ſtone <hi>Asbeſtos Plinie</hi> mentions, which once fired, can hardly ever be quenched. The waters of the deluge fell in 40 dayes, but were almoſt a year in drying; De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſtations are quickly made, the reparations ſlowly. But what talke I of reparations? This is our genrall fault, we miſtake a poſſibility for a certainty: like a raw gameſter, who as ſoon as he gets his men over the tables, thinkes all his own, till a blot fetch him backe to an <hi>after-opinion</hi> as well as <hi>game.</hi> I wiſh we may not anticipate our happineſs, and ſpoyle our game by preſuming it too forward. For my part, I thinke all proviſion we can make little enough, and, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Gods bleſſing, inſufficient.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The formerly mentioned are but our working dayes abuſes, now followes our ſeventh and Sabbaticall errour, wherein we ſeeme to reſt, and which compleats the weeke of our miſcarriages.</p>
               <p>The moſt naturall humour in man, is ſelf-love, the moſt violent, Ambition: that, enclines him to profit, this, to dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. Theſe two are like <hi>Rebecca's</hi> twins continually ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling for precedency. Ambition like <hi>Eſau,</hi> nips the other for a time, and preſſes out firſt; but (violent things not long ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſiſting) Self-love like <hi>Jacob,</hi> ſoon deprives it of its birth-right. To men ſet in office, at the beginning every little authority ſeemes great, while their <hi>eyes ſee double,</hi> dazled with the dignity: afterward every great ſeemes little, time having wrought off the novelty, and turned the view ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way: for now having <hi>crackt the ſhell, they ſeeke the kernell.</hi> Popularity for a while maintaines Integrity, but time corrupts both. Many great Patriots in the beginning, have ſince byaſed: Gaine hath been to them like the golden ball throwne downe before <hi>Atalanta,</hi> which ſhe ſtepping a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide and ſtooping to take up, her race was hindred. The
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113079:12"/>Hebrew word for gold is therefore pithy, as derived from a root, which ſignifies ſolicitude and diſtraction. Men natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally go down the hill, and propend to ſelf-Intereſt, and this paſſion is ſo prevalent, it can hardly be maſtred, but by that other of feare; as we uſe to hunt one beaſt with another. There would be no wickedneſs, if there were no protectours of wicked men, and permiſſion is protection.</p>
               <p>Why ſhould a few Accomptants ſtand up like <hi>Hercules</hi> Colomnes, which no man dares outrepaſſe. You, that have ſmitten the <hi>Lion</hi> and the <hi>Beare,</hi> ſhall a <hi>Cocks crowing</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fright? Have you loſt your courage with your money? and the mettall of your mindes with that of your purſes? if not, why are not money-mongers called to account? why muſt the Commiſſioners of examination for accounts have a lame and curtayld power? why muſt taxes run on in <hi>infini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> and no body know what becomes of them? It's an old maxime. Acquaint the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons with, what is done, and they will thinke it done for common good, otherwiſe for private profit. If theſe men were innocent, me thinkes, they ſhould be glad to vindicate their innocence, and wipe off the ſtains, which blemiſh it: nay, if others were innocent, me thinkes, it ſhould concerne them, to give the Kingdome this ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Sure there are <hi>Receavers</hi> as well as <hi>theeves,</hi> who oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion all this tergiverſation. What's the reaſon elſe, that notwithſtanding the impoſition of Exciſe, continuation of all former taxes, addition of new, and turning the ſtreame of the Aſſociation money, yet there is ſuch extreme penu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that our Army ſcarce payed wants recruits, <hi>Taunton</hi> cannot be relieved without begging for it, nothing of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment done without freſh ſupplyes? Can we ſee this and not bluſh to be ſo notoriouſly gull'd? I ſay notoriouſly, ſince all Europe takes notice of it, and laughs at our ſimplicity. <hi>Ob.</hi> 1. Some have alleaged formerly, that if we ſhould not connive at petty abuſes, we could not be ſupplyed with great
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113079:13"/>ſums in time of extremity. Call you thoſe abuſes petty, which make us a ſcorne and deriſion to all our neighbours? Againe, what puts you upon theſe extremities, but your own ſupine Careleſneſſe? like ſome ill husbands, who rather then trouble their heads with care of their eſtates, remit all unto their Stewards, and if by them they may be furniſhed for the preſent (although with ſpoyle of their woods, and other ſquandring ſhifts) never dreame of the future, till by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, they enſlave themſelves to their owne ſervants, who often buy them out of all with their owne money. Were it not better to call your Stewards to a weekly account, and order your expences according to your incomes? Can we ever looke to thrive, untill we know upon what ground we build? nay, with what face can we exhauſt the Kingdome, under pretence of bringing Delinquents to juſtice, while we cheriſh as great Delinquents in our owne boſomes? Beſides, its folly to imagine we ſhall alwayes have theſe Monopoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zers of Treaſure, within our call: as long as there is hope of further gaine, they will inch out our neceſſities, but in time of extreme danger, what hinders them, their eſtates being portable, to tranſport them, and leave us, like men at a low water, upon the ſands? for if we thinke them guilty, we cannot imagine them ſo ſilly as to ſtay a whipping.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ob.</hi> 2. Others allow of this motion, but not of this time, as thinking it now unſeaſonable, and that it would retard the preſent proſecution of the buſineſs. Before the reliefe of <hi>Taunton,</hi> many honeſt active Citizens were forwarding this good worke, as rightly apprehending it the only effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious meanes, to make ſtraite what was crooked, and reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver our priſtine ſtrength: but they were ſtaved off with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes of our then preſent extremities. Now that God hath blowne away our enemies with the breath of his indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and bleſſed us with ſufficient leaſure to dreſſe our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and provide againſt future wounds; we are told this is
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:113079:13"/>a time to <hi>reap corne,</hi> not to <hi>pick ſtrawes</hi> in; a time to <hi>chaſe in the field,</hi> not to <hi>ſit potching at home.</hi> Thus the winter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too cold, and the ſummer too hot; I wonder what time of yeare, theſe men would have us worke in.</p>
               <p>We ſtart well, but we purſue not: why did you ſhow your teeth at Guild-hall, if you intended not to bite? or if you be, indeed, ſtill hungry, when can you expect more lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, to make a meale of theſe all-devouring pikes? can there ever be a fitter time to ſqueeze the ſpunges in (if any ſuch there be, as it's mainly to be feared) then now, that we want money to compleat our victory, with our Army? Search but the Tents of theſe <hi>Achans,</hi> and doubt not, you will find <hi>gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den wedges,</hi> and <hi>ſilver ſhekels,</hi> enough to ſtop the Souldiers mouthes one quarter, perhaps encourage them ſo far, that the worke will be halfe done by the next quarter. It's the property of <hi>quick-ſilver,</hi> to erect and ſet up an end: if the Souldier be <hi>quickſhod</hi> with this mettall, its incredible how ayrie his ſpirits will be, and how nimble-handed he will be to every enterprize. Falſhood is a Viper which wounds with her teeth, and bears the cure in her belly: Some horſe-lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches are ſo full, that if you purge them not, they will die of a ſurfeit.</p>
               <p>If I thought all that are in our Iſrael, were of our Iſrael, it were bootleſſe to ſtir you up to ſuch a duty: I would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>ſound this Alarum</hi> throughout the whole land, that all may come out of the caves and dens, wherein they were hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and as one man purſue the enemy. But ſeeing moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to do their duty except hired thereto, and ſeeing its hard to follow the chaſe we are in, without continuall freſh ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies; I hold it impoſſible to raiſe theſe conſtant ſupplies, except the people be firſt ſatisfied in this particular. Field action, and City conſultation, are not like clock weights, when one mounts the other deſcends: they are rather incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated twins, which muſt alwayes move together. When
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:113079:14"/>the ſouldier is buſieſt in action, the Senator ſhould be moſt aſſiduous in Counſell.</p>
               <p>To conclude then, there is no ſo ready meane to unty this Gordian knot, as my Lord Majors Sword, I mean another City Petition, preſſed with all modeſt earneſtneſſe upon the Parliament, to Audit the Accounts of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom with all the ſpeed imaginable, for if you follow not the ſcent, whiles it is yet warme, the next wind of ſucceſſe blows it quite away.</p>
               <p>Flatter not your ſelves, neither plucke too early, the fruits of your labours: remember from whence we are rayſed, by whom, and whither we may fall againe. Whats the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of that marvellous viciſſitude hath been hitherto in our affaires? our crying up man too much, too little crying up to God. Confidence and ſecurity are the forerunners of danger: preſent ſucceſſe hath only freed the paſſage, and opened the way: we are far yet from our journeys end, if you deſire a <hi>ſudden end,</hi> provide for a <hi>long journey,</hi> if a <hi>haſty peace,</hi> for a <hi>ſlow War,</hi> not to make it ſo, but as if it were ſo. This proviſion cannot be better made then by redreſſing exciſe abuſes, and ſo ſetling it for the future, that the people may be both ſatisfied and freed by <hi>frequent accounts,</hi> which would produce <hi>rare taxes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The advantage of this redreſſe and ſettlement would be great. The Parliaments honour would be hereby vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, who ſuffer extreamely in the opinion of thoſe, who want the ſpirit of diſcerning between ſound and unfound. The hands and hearts of our friends would be ſtrengthned, when they ſhould ſee their money as faithfully <hi>diſtributed,</hi> as cordially <hi>exhibited.</hi> The countenances of all wicked <hi>Cains</hi> would fall, when they ſhould ſee us in a conſtant courſe of ſupply no more lyable to the <hi>ſhoales</hi> of want, or <hi>rockes</hi> of cozenage.</p>
               <p>Beſides hereby we ſhould be inabled to rayſe freſh for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:113079:14"/>in the Eaſterne aſſociation, by ſuffering the currant of their monies to reſume their proper channel. Neither would this be of ſmall moment, whenas the Generall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged from the particular care of thoſe Counties, (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his army ſeems yet tyed by receipt of their pay,) ſhould not need eye any other buſneſſe, then purſuance of the King and the hindrance of his recruits: Then, the virtue of this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample would worke upon other Counties, and animate them to the like aſſociation, by not fearing (as they have hitherto had cauſe) a diverſion of their levies, when they ſhould ſee a ſollid eſtabliſhment for our owne. Its incredible what order and due proportion will do in taxes. The united provinces with leſſe then two millions of reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue maintaine a hundred thouſand men on foot, whereof <hi>Amſterdam</hi> more then a third part. And if the Dutch fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gality be compared with our Engliſh profuſion, I ſee no reaſon why <hi>London</hi> may not exceed <hi>Amſterdams</hi> proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or ſince the Beere exciſe amounts there to ſixty thouſand pound a yeare, why it may not here be farmed at one hundred thouſand pound, or if you will ſay their multitude of Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, (who are uſually troubled with dry livers) may make them proportionably exceed us in that particular; Sure we exceed them more in other domeſtick, &amp; frivolous expences. Vnequall and jumping taxes undoe us, while no man knows how to proportion his expences: how much better were it, both for the Common-wealth and us to be at a certainty? Wherefore I will <hi>wind up my alarum</hi> with a relation of the low Country exciſe as it was ſent me laſt weeke out of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> which although not altogether ſo perfect, as I deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, vet may afford ſome light in things moſt materiall, and ſtir up others to licke this rude draught into better forme, which hath been my maine intention.</p>
               <p>But before the <hi>voyder</hi> come give me leave, inſtead of a <hi>Deſſert</hi> to ſerve you with one caution more. That as we have new
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:113079:15"/>modelized our army, and ought to new modelize our exciſe, ſo (if we really aime at a ſpeedy period of our miſeries) we muſt new Modelize ſomething elſe of greateſt concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. If we looke into the <hi>Venetian</hi> government, we ſhall find their ſo much admired durability and proſperity to flow from the frequent redintegration of their ſeverall Committees or Councells by their grand Counſell. Thus precedent Counſells were obſcured by the <hi>Septemviri,</hi> and theſe againe by the <hi>Decemviri,</hi> who beare an annuall ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy, and are accountable at the years end, to be accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their merits, either puniſhed or rewarded. In the Infancy of the low-Country Common-wealth, their chiefe Counſell, was that of State, wherto both Governour and Generall, had and have admittance, but ſoone after ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending the danger wherto they expoſed themſelves, by revealing the miſteries of their State to ſtrangers, and yet not daring openly to diſguſt the Engliſh, they ordained a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother ſupreme Councell, whereto their Generall hath no admittance; whereby they ſatisfied the Earle of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> and ſecured themſelves. When our forraign friends ſaw us begin the yeare ſo reſolutely with execution of Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents, and removall of remiſſe Agents, they verily thought the houre of our deliverance come, and expected we ſhould have ſtopt at no mediums but gone roundly on to the end propoſed. What meane then al theſe rubs and ſuddain ſtops, which come upon us like fits of the <hi>falling ſickneſſe?</hi> The ice is broken, and we on the other ſide of <hi>Rubicon,</hi> by the <hi>cure</hi> of our <hi>feet</hi> and reformation of our armies. The <hi>reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of our withered hands,</hi> is the worke of another <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath,</hi> of ſuch a day of reſt wherewith God hath now bleſſed us, and is accompliſhed by <hi>opening the palmes</hi> of all recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers; whereof enough hath been ſaid, if rightly, too much, if ſlightly underſtood. But both theſe remedies are inſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, as long as the ſame <hi>evill ſpirit</hi> that <hi>poſſeſſed</hi> hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:113079:15"/>the <hi>executive,</hi> now <hi>torments the directive power.</hi> When the feet are lame, there is help by crutches, when our hands faile us, others may feed us, but the diſtraction of the head, hath an influence upon all the ſenſes: It lies neither in the <hi>forepart</hi> nor in the <hi>hinderpart</hi> it is in <hi>vertice.</hi> The only mean to chaſe away this <hi>evill ſpirit,</hi> is the <hi>harp of David,</hi> i.e. the ſlip of unity grafted in the ſtock of honeſty: a true harmony between all the honeſt both in Parliament and City.</p>
               <p>Seeing God hath abounded in mercy towards you, be not wanting to your ſelves; when God goes before he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects you ſhould remoove your tents and follow him, and that not halting but running. Wherefore either let former ſucceſſe animate you, or abundance of future feare drive away all preſent feare. Relapſes are dangerous, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as the diſeaſe diminiſheth, ſo care of the patient ought to be augmented.</p>
               <p>I deſire peace, no man more: yet let me tell you, thoſe who have drawne their ſword againſt their Prince (rational men wil underſtand me in a vulgar ſence) I wil not ſay with <hi>Alexander</hi> of <hi>Parma</hi> ſhould fling away their ſcabbard, but ſurely ſhould be cautious, upon what tearmes they ſheath it. <hi>The Key of the Kings Cabinet, as it hath unlockt the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of former Treaties, ſo I hope it will locke up our minds from thoughts of future.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:113079:16"/>
            <head>A Treatiſe of Exciſe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince there is no Peace without a previous War, nor war without ſtipends, neither ſtipends without taxes; and ſince this is eſpecially remarkable in the United Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, whoſe ſeverall Signories, are bound to a yearly tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute for defence of the common Cauſe; it will not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe to looke more narrowly into the Collection of thoſe riches, which have rendred <hi>Holland,</hi> the miracle of this latter age.</p>
            <p>Tributes here are of two ſorts, ſome ordinary, others extraordinary. Ordinary are thoſe, which once impoſed, are ever after exacted. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, ſuch as according to the vaniſhing or imminent neceſſity of the Common-wealth, are ſometimes exacted, ſometimes remitted.</p>
            <p>I find three ſorts of extraordinary taxes; the firſt is of every head, the ſecond of every Chimney, the third is upon the whole bulke of a mans wealth and poſſeſſions balanced together. That is called <hi>Head-money,</hi> the other <hi>Chimney money,</hi> and this <hi>the two hundreth penny.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Poll-money</hi> conſiſts in two ſhillings, which the Common-wealth hath for every head within it. Which how it ſwels their Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurie, is eaſie to conjecture, by the infinite frequency of its Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants. Yet men of meaneſt condition are exempt from this burden, and thoſe accounted ſuch, who ſhame not to profeſſe their extreme poverty before the Cenſors. This hath been but once, that ever I could heare of exacted, with great reluctancy of the people, whereof ſome appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently withſtood it, which may be the reaſon of its intermiſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chimney-money,</hi> is nothing elſe, but a tribute, which owners of houſes, whether in Countrey or City, pay in behalf of their Chimneys, for every one two ſhillings. Herein the Spaniards in the Kingdome of <hi>Naples</hi> preceded the <hi>Low-country</hi> men, for this Cuſtome is yet there obſerved.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The two hundreth part,</hi> is aſſeſſed upon the whole bulke of a mans ſubſtance, ſo that whoever is worth two hundred ſhillings or pounds, payes in one to the Treaſury, for foure hundred two, and ſo propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionably: but may ſome ſay, How can the Magiſtrate make a true
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:113079:16"/>eſtimate of every mans private fortunes? Since none eaſily betray their opulence or indigence; Whence may be infer'd, that the Magiſtrate often declines the way of equity, ſeeing it cannot be, but that ſome will paſſe for poorer, others for richer then indeed they are. This difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is prevented by a prudent temper and moderation. For the cuſtome is, that in impoſing this <hi>two hundreth,</hi> the Conſuls and other City Magiſtrates, according to publick fame of every ones wealth and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, exact from ſome more from ſome leſſe, as they are vulgarly eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med wealthy or needy: whereby no man is forced to reveale his riches, which are rated at the arbitrement of the Magiſtrate, and common rumour. Notwithſtanding, if any will upon oath affirme himſelfe over-rated, what is juſt and equitable, is detracted.</p>
            <p>In which proceeding this is obſervable, that moſt men being ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, and affecting the repute of opulent, many from whom the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate exacts too much, chuſe rather to pay, then proclaime the ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe of their fortunes. So that vice it ſelfe ſupports vertue, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all profit is reaped from wealth imaginary. This tribure is for the moſt part trienniall.</p>
            <p>Ordinary taxes are manifold, I will only hint at the principall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Salt Exciſe</hi> is thus exacted. The City Magiſtrate uſeth to view each family, and the perſons thereof, and according as the family is leſſe or more numerous, a greater or leſſer meaſure of Salt is preſumed to be annually ſpent, and proportionably a greater or leſſer ſumme im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed. In ſome Cities there is a certaine price appointed to every great and ſmall meaſure, which the buyer payes in lieu of tribute.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Beere exciſe,</hi> whereto all Citizens are promiſcuouſly bound, is of twenty pence a barrell. Only ſmalleſt Beere of three ſhillings the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell is Exciſe free, in favour of the poore. Beſides the aforeſaid, all Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes and Inne-keepers, pay two ſhillings three pence the barrell. The exciſe which Brewers alone diſcharge, is two pence upon every barrell. So much likewiſe pay the Mariners or Merchants, who im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port Beere from <hi>England, Germany,</hi> and elſe-where.</p>
            <p>Upon <hi>French wines</hi> ſix pence a gallon. Upon <hi>Spaniſh, Reniſh, and other ſorts,</hi> twelve pence the gallon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vinegar Exciſe</hi> conſiſts of ſix ſhillings eight pence upon every Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of 40 gallons, two pence the Gallon.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Strong waters,</hi> and <hi>Aquavita</hi> is impoſed ten pence the gallon, if made of Wine; five pence if of Beere,</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:113079:17"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Butter exciſe,</hi> conſiſts of ſix ſhillings eight pence upon every bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell of three hundred and twenty pounds, a farthing upon every pound; multitude of pounds ſupplying the defect of magnitude in the impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oyle exciſe,</hi> conſiſts of ſix ſhillings eight pence the Pipe; upon each Veſſell of Whale Oyle, five ſhillings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Candle exciſe,</hi> both of Wax and Tallow, is foure ſhillings two pence the hundred, half a penny the pound.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The impoſt of round meaſure,</hi> is that which is upon all ſuch Wares as are meaſured with meaſures of a round forme, as Corne, Salt, Seeds, Lime <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for every <hi>last</hi> or <hi>load of wheat,</hi> one ſhilling ten pence, of <hi>Rye</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">s</hi>.1<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. <hi>of round and ſmall ſeed,</hi> three ſhillings. For a hundred pound of Salt, three ſhillings and a penny <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now this exciſe is payed by thoſe Merchants, who buy great quantities and meaſures of theſe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Turfe</hi> and <hi>Coale exciſe,</hi> conſiſts in one peny and a halfe, the tun of Turfe; and one pound ten ſhillings upon a hundred pound, of great Engliſh or Scotch coales.</p>
            <p>Exciſe of ruder and harder Wares, vulgarly the <hi>Impost of great wares,</hi> conſiſts in five pence the hundred of Lead, two pence the thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand of Brick.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wood exciſe</hi> conſiſts in the eighth penny of what it is ſold for; ſo that if it be 8 or 12 ſhillings the load the Exciſe is 1 ſhilling, or 1 ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſix pence.</p>
            <p>Exciſe of <hi>Cloathes interweaved with gold, and of all ſilke,</hi> conſiſts in the twelfth penny of every ell, ſo that if it be ſold for twelve ſhillings, the Common-wealth hath one, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon every one of their owne <hi>woollen clothes,</hi> ten ſhillings. Upon <hi>Engliſh cloathes</hi> undied, for every peece valued at 12 pound, one pound; and for every peece above 12 pounds value, one pound ſix ſhillings eight pence, upon the courſeſt Cloathes, two pence the ell.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Tapiſtry</hi> and <hi>guilt leather,</hi> and ſuch kind of Wares, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the ninth penny of their value. The value is enquired of the Merchant, who leaſt he ſhould coſen the Farmer of this Exciſe, by diſſembling and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhing the true price, it is prudently ordained, that paying one Fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh pound, <hi>i.e.</hi> ten ſhillings more then the Merchants price is, the Farmer may (if he thinke good) retaine thoſe. Wares as ſold to himſelfe.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:113079:17"/>
            <p>Upon each <hi>Waggon</hi> and <hi>Boat</hi> two ſhillings: for <hi>greater veſſels</hi> more, according to the number of their Tunnes. Ten ſhillings upon every Coach.</p>
            <p>The Exciſe of <hi>manured lands,</hi> conſiſts in foure pence halfe peny the Acre, with whatſoever ſowne or planted, to be paid every moneth; the Months to be counted from the ſowing time untill Harveſt.</p>
            <p>Upon all ſorts of land, the ſixth penny of what they are <hi>let</hi> for. And if any hire not, but live upon their owne lands, they are eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Magiſtrate.</p>
            <p>Upon <hi>houſes,</hi> the eighth penny of their rent; but becauſe the rent is not alwayes one and the ſame, therfore their eſtimate is taken by the Magiſtrate, and the proprietaries more or leſſe rated.</p>
            <p>For every ſervant, the Maſter or Miſtris payes two ſhillings.</p>
            <p>Exciſe of all <hi>immooveables,</hi> wherein ſhips are comprehended, conſiſts of the fourtieth part of the price for which they are ſold. Which, how much it conduceth to the encreaſe of their Treaſurie, may be infer'd from their frequent ſale of immooveables in <hi>Holland,</hi> teſtified by that Proverb; <hi>Once in three years half the City of</hi> Leyden <hi>is ſold &amp; alienated.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Exciſe of the <hi>great</hi> and <hi>ſmall Seale,</hi> conſiſts in two pence upon every ſheet ſealed with the leſſer, a groat upon every ſheet ſealed with the greater. For you muſt know, The States of <hi>Holland,</hi> for this tributes ſake only, have decreed, that no Wils or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts, or any other Deeds valnable in law, that no Petitions; and laſtly, that nothing which ſhould be admitted into publick Courts of Judicature, and Tribunals, ought to be written otherwiſe then in theſe leaves ſtamped with the States Seale. The Seale was made divers, in regard of the greater or leſſer moment of what is to be Sealed.</p>
            <p>Many other ſpecies of Exciſe they have, which would be tedious to deſcribe; <hi>Ex vngue Leonem,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But when the manner of their Collection was debated by the States; Some judged it moſt expedient to ordaine in every City, ſome City Magiſtrates, or other mercenary Officers, who ſhould take care of the Common-wealths revenue, thinking it unſafe and prejudiciable, to farme out the taxes for a certain ſum of money, &amp; that for theſe reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe publick perſons are more authoritative then private; and Authority ſeemes wholly neceſſary in a thing ſo odious, as is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action of Tribute.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe the annuall profit of ſome taxes is uncertaine, as of thoſe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:113079:18"/>of wine, and beere, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for example, in the ſame City ſometimes 100, ſometimes one hundred and fifty tunnes of wine are conſumed; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the exciſe of wine cannot be farmed out at a certaine rate. For the Farmers will redeeme the exciſe either for more or for leſſe then they afterwards make thereof; If for more, the farmer looſeth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, if for leſſe, the Common-wealth ſuſtains the dammage.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They added, that their Cities grew yearly more populous, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently the taxes would grow more profitable; wherefore if they ſhould be let for any terme of yeares for a certain annuall ſumme, the loſſe of the Common-wealth would be too ſenſible.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Laſtly they affirmed it perillous to intruſt private men with pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like revenews; for what if thoſe Farmers promiſe much and performe nothing? how if they therewith patch up private neceſſities? nay how, if they are found unable to ſatisfy their yearly penſion! where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thoſe things which without, the Common-wealth cannot ſubſiſt, ought to be in its immediate diſpoſall.</p>
            <p>Others were of opinion, that the exciſe ought to be let out to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate men, for certaine annuall ſummes, they had obſerved a two fold ſort of taxes; ſome impoſed on certaine commodities, and ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe their revenew was certaine: As what is impoſed on houſes and grounds, is as certaine, as is their number and quantity. Other taxes are uncertaine as the commodities whereon they are impoſed; ſuch are thoſe of wine and beere whereof now more, now leſſe is expended: looke how uncertaine the quantity of theſe is, ſo uncertaine is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of their exciſe. Wherefore they thought fit, for the collection of the former as aſſured and conſtant, to employ a publike overſeer: but to farme out the latter as uncertaine for a certaine ſumme of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, for which opinion they urged theſe reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe theſe taxes are ſubject to infinite fraud and cozenage, whereby the Subjects elude their payment. Theſe deceits will be moſt diligently enquired into by private farmers, as reaping ſo much the more profit, by how much the more carefull they are to detect and avert thoſe frauds. For men are uſualy more ſolicitous about their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Wealth, then for the Common-wealth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Thoſe private men would be armed with authority ſufficient: For after the contract made for exaction of tribute, the Magiſtrate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſts them with convenient power, and they become, in a manner, publique perſons.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:113079:18"/>
            <p n="3">3. They added, becauſe the profit of theſe taxes was uncertaine, they were of neceſſity to be farmed at a certaine revenew; for its more behoovefull for the Common-wealth to be aſſured of ſomething then to have uncertaine revenues, for ſo they might meaſure their enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes by the rule of their revenew, If the farmers promiſe more then they receive, their contract obliges them to ſolve their annuall pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, if the receipts exceed the rents, the profit likewiſe redounds to the Publike. For when the ſame exciſe comes to be farmed againe the next yeare at a publike auction, either the old farmer caught with the benefit or others tolled on by hopes of the ſame gaine, will prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer a greater ſumme for redemption of the ſame taxes.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They profeſſed their intention to let out the exciſe only from yeare to yeare, or every ſix monthes, that ſo according to the meliorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Cities condition, the incomes of the Common-wealth might be yearly augmented.</p>
            <p>Laſtly they affirmed the danger was in vaine pretended, of intruſting private men with publike wealth, for that feare and thoſe miſchiefs were eaſily prevented, by the farmers preſentation of ſufficient ſureties. It might alſo be ordained; that a proportionable part of his yearly rent, be by the farmer paied in monthly to the treaſury.</p>
            <p>This laſt opinion was generally embraced and is to this day fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed; for although its impoſſible to avoyde all abuſes, ſince no man can be imagined to undergoe the hazard of ſuch an office without great apparence of great gaine, yet that loſſe is but a fleabiting in compariſon of what the Common-wealth now ſuffers by the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of ſuperfluous officers, who conſume needleſſely more then two hundred thouſand pound <hi>per annum</hi> as its eaſy to demonſtrate.</p>
            <p>Now the manner of letting out the exciſe is thus, Every yeare, or ſix months, the States of every City, by their printed edicts affixed in all publike places, ſeaſonably give notice of their intention at ſuch a ſet time and place, to let out this or that exciſe to whoſoever offers moſt, with thoſe cautions and conditions contained in their edicts. At the day appointed, the States deputies by publike cryers, ſet upon the wrack the redemption of the foreſaid exciſe. The farmer is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently compelled to bring in ſufficient ſureties, that the Common-wealth receive no detriment. For if the farmer fayle in his payment, the ſureties goods are ſeized for publike ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>For prevention of all deceit whereby the Citizen might defraud the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:113079:19"/>farmers two things are profitably inſtituted. 1. All porters carriers watermen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> who carry any wares lyable to exciſe are ſolemnly ſworne to bring no ſuch wares into any private houſe, before he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a note from the farmer, whereby he acknowledges himſelfe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſatisfied. 2. Extraordinary fines are ſet upon all ſuch as are found to have never ſo little deceived the farmer. For offences eaſily perpetrated, and which are very lucrative, can hardly be prevented, unleſſe by ſevereſt puniſhment.</p>
            <div type="postscript">
               <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
               <p>THe dying husbandman in the fable willing to engage his ſonnes in a future courſe of induſtry, recommended to them a hidden trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in his vineyard: They encouraged with theſe hopes fell ſuddenly to ſo laborious a digging that although they found no treaſure yet their vineyard was hereby ſoone mannur'd and fenced: If honeſt men would be induced to take a little pains in the grand buſineſſe of accounts, beſides the probability, of finding a reall treaſure, we ſhould at leaſt reap this benefit, that by our digging herein, the fruit of the vineyard would be improved for the future. As we are in our diet, ſo too often are we in our Councells; we tye our ſelves to beife and mutton, and ſcorne ſmaller diſhes as french Kick ſhaws, we looke only upon the <hi>Groſſe</hi> of a buſines and thinke the <hi>Beife</hi> (as I may ſay) <hi>of affaires</hi> only worthy our thoughts, neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting certaine <hi>circumſtantiall points,</hi> which <hi>are moſt eſſentiall</hi> and not conſidering that in Politickes accidents are <hi>ſubſtantiall.</hi> Becauſe we have the name of an exciſe among us, we thinke all is done, whereas untill we ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle all particulars nothing indeed can be effected. I know no reaſon why the benefit of all impoſitions, from the <hi>Crowne</hi> to the <hi>ticket office,</hi> ſhould not redound to the publike; This was impoſſible perhaps in the beginning; now the <hi>harveſt</hi> is ripe, and its high time to uſe the <hi>fickle.</hi>
               </p>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Chi non può dar ál aſino dia ál baſto.</hi>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
